Guide to the Vassar College Natural History Museum Records, 1866-1969 (bulk 1906-1944)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Natural History Museum Records
1866-1969
1906-1944
Vassar College Natural History Museum
0.4 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection contains correspondence between Natural History Museum administrators, other museums and educational institutions, and vendors and collectors; annual reports; inventories and lists of specimens kept by the museum; clippings about the museum; advertisements for, and descriptions of, various anatomical and biological specimens and models; records of specimen loans and purchases; and floor plans for a proposed addition to the New England Building.
Historical Note
In late 1862, seeing a need for Vassar students to have the same first-hand access to science education specimens as their male counterparts, the Vassar College trustees hired Henry A. Ward, a professor of natural sciences at the University of Rochester, to put together a "cabinet" collection of scientific specimens. Ward's cabinet, conceived of as a teaching tool comprised mostly of geological and mineralogical specimens, was installed by 1864 and was housed in Main Building. In 1865, Sanborn Tenney was hired as Vassar's first professor of Natural History, as well as the first curator of the Collection. In 1874, the college decided to move the Collection to the nearby Calisthenium and Riding Academy in order to create more space in Main. On February 22, 1875, the newly named Vassar College Museum of Natural History celebrated its grand opening.
The Museum became home to numerous historically and scientifically important artifacts and included a comprehensive assortment of books about birds, the subjects of which ranged from the aesthetic lure of birds to scientific discussions of migration, anatomy, and physiology. One of the greatest possessions in the collection was a specimen of the extinct bird the Great Auk. The Vassar Auk was of particular importance because it was the specimen that John James Audubon had used in his descriptions of the bird.
In 1918, in order to create more classroom space, the Museum was moved to the New England Building. The museum in the New England Building extended from the first floor to the third, with collections being displayed both on the stair landings as well as in the central hall of the third floor. The impressive collection included nearly 3,000 mounted birds, a majority of the North American species, most of which were gathered together by James Orton and Poughkeepsie resident Jacob P. Giraud.
In 1979, multiple factors, including the poor state of the collection and a need for more classroom space, spurred the decision to start phasing out the museum. With its closure, the remaining collections were distributed among various national and state institutions. In 1992, what was left of the museum was moved to the first floor of Ely Hall. In April 2006, the museum, now called the A. Scott Warthin Museum of Geology and Natural History, celebrated its re-opening, complete with a newly renovated space and new display cases.
Source: "Natural History Museum," Vassar College Encyclopedia, 2007.
Chronology of Museum Curators
1865-1869 Sanborn Tenney (Professor of Natural History)
1869-1877 James Orton (Professor of Natural History)
1878-1906 William Buck Dwight (Professor of Natural History)
1906-1936 Aaron L. Treadwell (Professor of Zoology)
1937-1963 Rudolf T. Kempton (Professor of Zoology)
[1964?]-1969 Madelene E. Pierce (Professor of Zoology)
[1970?]-1977 Margaret R. Wright (Professor of Biology)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence between Natural History Museum administrators, other museums and educational institutions, and vendors and collectors. Also included are annual reports, inventories and lists of specimens kept by the museum, clippings about the museum, advertisements for and descriptions of various anatomical and biological specimens and models, records of specimen loans and purchases, and floor plans for a proposed addition to the New England Building.
Arranged alphabetically.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Jacob Post Giraud, Jr. Papers
Margaret Wright Papers
William Buck Dwight Papers
James Orton Papers.
The Vassar College Archives Files contains records of the Natural History Museum prior to 1900.
The Vassar College Subject Files contains additional files on the Natural History Museum.
Subject Headings
Names:
Kempton, Rudolf T.; Pierce, Madelene E.; Treadwell, Aaron L. (Aaron Louis), 1866-1947
Organizations:
Vassar College. Department of Biology; Vassar College. Department of Natural History; Vassar College. Department of Zoology; Vassar College. New England Building
Subjects:
Natural History--Study and teaching; Natural History Museums--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie
Document Types:
Clippings; Correspondence; Financial records; Floor Plans
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Administrative Offices and Functions
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, October 2023.
Acquisition Information
Unknown. Presumably transferred from the Biology Department in the 1980s.
Container List
- Advertisements, anatomical and natural history specimens (French and German), circa 1890s (Folder 1)
- Annual reports, 1916-1938 (Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1939-1948 (Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1906 (Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1907 (Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1908 (Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1909 (Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1910 (Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1911 (Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1912 (Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1913 (Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1914-1917 (Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1925 (Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1926 (Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1927 (Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1928 (Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1929-1930 (Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1931 (Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1932-1933 (Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1934 (Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Folder 24)
- Correspondence, circa 1963-1969 (Folder 25)
- Correspondence regarding mollusks and shells, circa 1923-1944 (Folder 26)
- Correspondence: Palmer, Ralph S., regarding the Great Auk and other bird specimens, 1942; (photocopies) (Folder 27)
- "Criticism Invited Upon Vassar College Collection of North American Birds," visitor comment book, 1867-1871; [see catalog entry QH70.U52 P68 1867]
- Floor plans, "Addition to New England Building", 1934 (Folder 28)
- "Guide to the Museum of Natural History," by Aaron L. Treadwell, 1944-1945; [see catalog entry QH70.U52 P68 1945]
- "Guide to the Museum of Natural History," by Aaron L. Treadwell, 1950-1951; [see Vassar College Subject Files, Folder 20.36 ]
- Inventories of shells and other invertebrates, 1866, undated (Folder 29)
- "Inventory of Anthropological Exhibits and Storage in the New England Building", 1935 (Folder 30)
- Invoices, 1897, undated (Folder 31)
- List of North American birds not in the J.P. Giraud Collection, undated (Folder 32)
- Notes on museum cabinets and specimens, undated (Folder 33)